Guide to the Wetmore Family Papers
Yale University. Department of Manuscripts and Archives
Wetmore family papers
1638-1921
MS 548
Yale University. Department of Manuscripts and Archives
5.5
(12 boxes)
The papers consist of materials relating to George Peabody Wetmore and his family. Correspondence and other papers document the lives of several of Wetmore's ancestors and reflect his interest in New England history. The papers also include letter books and account books of the mercantile firms of Prosper Wetmore & Brothers and Joseph and Joshua Grafton.
Wetmore family
Immediate Source of Acquisition
The Wetmore Family Papers were given to Yale University Library by Edith and Maude Wetmore between 1942 and 1947.
Arrangement
The papers are arranged by format.
Related Materials
Some papers of the Rev. Izrahiah Wetmore II are in the Yale Divinity Library.
Scope and Contents
The collection consists of the papers of George Peabody Wetmore (1846-1921), governor of Rhode Island, 1885-1887, U.S. Senator, 1895-1913, and other papers collected by him. These papers, going back to the 17th century, reflect Wetmore's interest in New England history. Special emphasis is given to Rhode Island (especially Newport) and Massachusetts (especially Boston and Salem), and to the family names Dudley and Derby (to whom Wetmore was related through his mother), Wetmore, and Keteltas (to whom Wetmore was related through his wife). Some papers related to the Aaron Burr family have been transferred to the Burr Family Papers. The collection also contains some papers of General William Shepard (1737-1817; his daughter Nancy was Wetmore's paternal grandmother), who commanded the force which quelled Shays' Rebellion in 1787. (See the genealogical tables for the Wetmores and also for the Graftons, whose business correspondence forms a separate unit at the end of the collection.)
Wetmore's personal papers contain letters from many important Washington figures including Presidents Roosevelt and Taft. Among the most heavily represented of these correspondents are Elihu Root and John Hay. The letters are individually catalogued in the department manuscript catalog on microfiche.
Conditions Governing Access
The materials are open for research.
Biographical / Historical
GEORGE PEABODY WETMORE, 1846-1921
George Peabody Wetmore, son of William Shepard and Anstiss Derby (Rogers) Wetmore, was born August 2, 1846, in London, England, during a visit of his parents abroad. William Shepard Wetmore, who was a merchant in the China trade, established mercantile houses in China, South America, and New York City. His father, Seth Wetmore, was a judge, a member of the Vermont Legislature and of the Governor's Council, and a Fellow of the University of Vermont. The latter married Nancy Shepard, a daughter of General William Shepard of the Continental Army. The founder of the American branch of the Wetmore family was Thomas Whitmore, who came from England to Boston, Mass., in 1635, and removed to Wethersfield, Conn., about 1640. Several of George Peabody Wetmore's paternal ancestors were among the original patentees of Middletown, Conn. His mother's ancestors lived in Massachusetts. She was a descendant of the Rogers, Dudley Derby, Crowninshield, Pickman, and other well-known families.
Mr. Wetmore received his early education at the private schools of Messrs. Reed and Thurston and of the Rev. William C. Leverett in Newport, R. I. At Yale he was a member of Linonia.
After graduation he studied for two years at the Columbia Law School. He received the degree of LL.B. in 1869, and was admitted to the bars of Rhode Island and New York the same year. He had always taken an active interest in politics and in 1880, and again in 1884, was a presidential elector. He was elected governor of Rhode Island in 1885 and served two terms, but was defeated for a third term. He was a member of the commission that built the new Rhode Island State House at Providence. In 1894 he was elected as a Republican to the United States Senate, receiving the unanimous vote of the General Assembly in Senate, House, and joint convention. He was twice reëlected to the Senate, his last term ending March 4, 1913. In the Senate Mr. Wetmore was, first, chairman of the Committee on Manufactures, and then chairman of the Joint Committee on the Library for sixteen years. He was also a member of the Appropriations, District of Columbia, Naval Affairs, Public Buildings and Grounds, and other committees. He had a deep interest in the building up of the Navy and the development of the naval base in Narragansett Bay. He served as chairman of the joint commission appointed by Congress to prepare plans for the completion of the Capitol building in Washington; was chairman of the first Lincoln Memorial Commission and a member of the commission that erected the National Lincoln Memorial in Washington; and was a member of the Grant Memorial Commission, as well as many others for the erection of statues and memorials. He was greatly interested in the improvement and development of Washington and the District of Columbia on a definite artistic plan, and was particularly identified with the legislation creating the National Commission of Fine Arts.
In private life Mr. Wetmore was for many years associated with various organizations for promoting the fine arts. He was one of the organizers of the Metropolitan Opera in New York and a member of the committee in charge of the construction of the Metropolitan Opera House. He was a trustee of the Peabody Museum of Natural History at Yale and of the Peabody Education Fund. In 1888 he was nominated as a Fellow of the University, but declined to have his name considered. He was one of the founders of the Jockey Club, vice-president of the National Horse Show Association of America, and a director of other organizations for improving the breeding of horses. At his home in Newport he was a trustee of the Redwood Library and Athenyæum, president and a trustee of the Newport Hospital, and president of the Newport Reading Room and the Newport Casino. He was a member of the Society of the Cincinnati.
He was married December 22, 1869, in New York City, to Edith Malvina Keteltas. Her father, Eugene Keteltas, was a member of the Class of 1822, Yale College, but left before graduation, and was graduated at Union College in 1822. Yale gave him the honorary degree of M.A. in 1870. Mrs. Wetmore's grandfather, Philip Doddridge Keteltas, was Yale 1792; her great-grandfather, Rev. Abraham Keteltas, graduated at Yale in 1752 and was admitted to the M.A. degree at Yale and Princeton in 1755; and her great-great-grandfather, William Smith, was Yale 1719. Mr. and Mrs. Wetmore had four children: Edith Malvina Keteltas; Maude Alice Keteltas; William Shepard Keteltas (B.A. 1897); and Rogers Pickman Derby Keteltas.
Mr. Wetmore died September 11, 1921, in Boston, Mass. The funeral services were held in Trinity Church, Newport, and the interment was in the Island Cemetery. He is survived by his wife and daughters and one son. His son, Rogers P. D. K. Wetmore, died April 26, 1917.
Yale College Obituary Record, 1920-1925 pp. 350-352.
Armed Forces; Business; Families; Law; Massachusetts -- Commerce; Massachusetts -- History; New England; Rhode Island -- History; Rhode Island -- Politics and government -- 1865-1950; United States -- History -- Colonial period, ca. 1600-1775; United States -- History -- Revolution, 1775-1783; United States -- Politics and government -- 1865-1900; United States -- Politics and government -- 1901-1953; Account books; Diaries; Lawyers; Legislators; Merchants; Politicians; Grafton, Joseph, 1755-1794; Grafton, Joshua, 1757-1787; Hay, John, 1769-1843; Root, Elihu, 1845-1937; Shepherd, William, 1737-1817; Wetmore, George Peabody, 1846-1921; Wetmore, Prosper, 1767-1817; Wetmore, William, 1749-1830; Whitmore family; Prosper Wetmore & Brothers
- Biographical data for some correspondents, with auction notices for some of the items purchased by GPW (other auction notices are filed with the items themselves) (Box 1)
- Autographs of some correspondents (Box 1)
- Correspondence, legal and business papers
  - 1638 (an 1821 copy), 1659-1802 (Box 1)
    General
    See also:box 8
  - 1803-1912 (Box 2)
    See also: box 8
  - 1913-1919, undated and miscellaneous (Box 3)
- Correspondence and notes of GPW re: collecting books (especially editions of William Smith's History of New York ) and portraits, 1913-1918 (Box 3)
- Diaries and journals
  - Thomas Paine (1694-1757): annotated copy of Edward Holyoke's Almanack of the Celestial Motions, Aspects and Eclipses, 1715 (Box 3)
  - Richard Derby (1736-1781): diary, mostly 1775 January-December (Box 3)
  - William Fisk (d. 1803)
    - Itinerary, 1776 December 16-1777 January 21 (Box 3)
    - Accounts, 1777 (Box 3)
  - Diary, "Copy from Joseph Bates Book", 1777 August 23-October 18 (Box 3)
  - Diary, "Copy of a memorandum kept by Elias Richards", 1777 May 25-1779 January 18 (Box 3)
  - John Francis (1763-1796), attributed author (see catalog card): "Journal of our Journey to Connecticut and Massachusetts to collect Debts", 1789 February 7-12 (Box 3)
  - Joseph Bowditch, Jr.: diary, 1797 January-December (Box 3)
  - William Wetmore (1749-1830): memorandum book and diary kept in interleaved copies of various almanacs, and bound in 6 volumes
    - Vol. 1, 1771-1779 (Box 4)
    - Vol. 2, 1799-1803 (Box 9)
    - Vol. 3, 1804-1809 (Box 10)
    - Vol. 4, 1810-1816 (Box 11)
    - Vol. 5, 1817-1823 (Box 12)
    - Vol. 6, 1824-1829 (Box 5)
- Notebooks and memorabilia
  - Notes in Latin and Dutch on the Old Testament prophetic books, bound with fragments of a printed textbook in Latin, Undated (Box 5)
    Material marked "Abraham Keteltas, 1780" (Keteltas, 1732-1798, Yale 1752, was the great-grandfather of GPW's wife Edith); presumably belonged to one of his Dutch ancestors.
  - GPW: notes taken at Columbia College Law School, probably on the lectures of Theodore William Dwight (1822-1892), Circa 1869 (Box 5)
  - Tribute from the Trustees of the Newport Hospital to GPW, 1921 September 13 (Box 5)
- Account books and business letterbooks (Box 6)
  - Prosper Wetmore & Brothers: ledger and journal of mercantile transactions, 1794-1799 (Box 6)
  - Joseph and Joshua Grafton, merchants of Salem, Massachusetts, and Havana, Cuba: 11 letterbooks, one bound, some numbered
    - #1, 1781 November-1782 June (Box 7)
    - #2, 1782 January-July (Box 7)
    - (bound), 1782 March-1784 December (Box 7)
    - # 5, 1782 October-1783 February (Box 7)
    - # 6, 1783 February-June (Box 7)
    - # 7, 1783 March-November (Box 7)
    - # 8, 1783 June-1784 March (Box 7)
    - # 9, 1783 November-1784 January (Box 7)
    - #11, 1784 April-June (Box 7)
    - 1785 January-May (Box 7)
    - 1786 January-May (Box 7)
- Folio
  - Correspondence, legal and business papers, 1685-1847 (Folder 8)
    See also: box 1
    See also: box 2
  - Autographed photograph of William H. Taft, 1909 May 8 (Folder 8)
  - Wetmore family genealogy, 1859 (Folder 8)